Records, 1886-1928 and undated
Smithsonian Institution Archives
Records
1886-1928 and undated
Smithsonian Institution Archives, Washington, D.C., osiaref@si.edu
United States National Museum, Division of Plants
SI Records
6.4 linear meters.
Record Unit 221
Historical Note
Joseph Nelson Rose, botanist, was born on a farm near Liberty, Indiana, on January 11, 1862. In 1881 he entered Wabash College, graduating with an A.B. in 1885. Rose stayed on at Wabash College as its first postgraduate student, receiving his A.M. in 1887 and his Ph.D. in 1889. During his last two years he acted as an assistant in botany under John M. Coulter, who was to have an influence on his later career.
Rose was appointed as an assistant botanist in the United States Department of Agriculture under George Vasey, working in the United States National Herbarium (USNH), in August 1888. (For a history of the USNH and George Vasey, see the description for the Hunt Institute collection 105.)
When the USNH was moved back to the Smithsonian in 1896, Rose transferred to the United States National Museum as an assistant curator, Division of Plants. In 1905 he was made associate curator.
Though Frederick Vernon Coville was honorary curator, USNH and the Division of Plants, in the United States National Museum (while at the same time chief botanist of the Plant Industry, USDA), it appears that Rose was directly in charge of the National Herbarium. Outgoing letterpress correspondence within these records contains copies of the USNH report for the Smithsonian Annual Report being transmitted by Coville through Rose and Rose's report on the Division of Plants for the Annual Report being sent to Coville. At times, Rose signed outgoing correspondence over the title, acting curator. Coville remained Rose's supervisor, however, with correspondence regarding Rose's collecting activities being transmitted between Smithsonian administrative officers and Coville.
In 1912, Rose transferred from the United States National Museum (USNM) to the Carnegie Institution of Washington as a research associate in order to prepare a monograph with Nathaniel Lord Britton on Cactaceae of the world. This work was jointly supported by the Carnegie Institution, the New York Botanical Garden, and the USDA. Rose was relieved of his administrative duties with the Smithsonian. Nonetheless, he retained an office in the Smithsonian and was allowed the use of Smithsonian franking privileges for all correspondence regarding his project, while retaining the title of custodian of "Cactaceae, Crassulaceae, and Miscellaneous Mexican Collections" in the National Herbarium.
Rose officially returned to the Smithsonian as associate curator, Division of Plants, in 1917, retaining that position until his death on May 4, 1928.
Rose's collecting activities and botanical studies began with the flora, fungi, and pine of Indiana and the Umbelliferae of North America. He was assigned the Mexican collections gathered by Edward Palmer while assistant botanist at the USDA. This led to 20 years of study of the flora of Mexico and numerous publications, including his "Studies of Mexican and Central America Plants," published in Contributions from the United States National Herbarium (1897-1911). His important study on Cactaceae of the world with Nathaniel Lord Britton resulted in the publication of four volumes titled The Cactaceae (1919-1923). Overall, Rose published almost 200 articles and monographs by himself and in collaboration with other botanists. Besides his own collecting explorations, Rose was instrumental in bringing to the Smithsonian one of its most important gifts, the large private herbarium and botanical library belonging to John Donnell Smith of Baltimore.
In reward for his botanical investigations and publications, Rose received an LL.D. from Wabash College in 1925. His remarks made during the ceremonies are included in this collection.
Introduction
This finding aid was digitized with funds generously provided by the Smithsonian Institution Women's Committee.
Descriptive Entry
These papers include official records that document the history of the USNH while Joseph Nelson Rose was assistant botanist at the United States Department of Agriculture (1888-1896), assistant and associate curator, USNH, United States National Museum (1896-1911), and the Division of Plants, USNM (1917-1928); also personal and official papers documenting Rose's professional career, including incoming and occasional loose outgoing correspondence after 1910 (watermarks on 1910 and 1911 outgoing loose correspondence along with virtually nonexistent outgoing letterpress correspondence after 1909 are a result of water damage to the records) with leading foreign and United States botanists; colleagues; herbarium and nursery curators; florists; agrostologists; field agents; amateur plant collectors; United States Department of Agriculture administrative officers; Smithsonian Institution administrative officers; agricultural experiment stations; editors; and friends. Correspondence regards examination, identification, and reports on botanical specimens; identification of specimens for publications; transfer of specimens to the USNH; exchange of specimens; requests to Rose regarding information on the flora of Texas and Mexico; requests for bulbs, seeds, and plants; purchasing of cacti collections; research and collecting expeditions; authorization for expeditions; nomenclature; illustrations for journals; collaboration over collecting specimens and publishing; requests for jobs; requests to recommend colleagues to systematize cultivated plants; proposals for a building to house the USNH in order to expand the collection; meetings of scientific societies; requests for Who's Who autobiographical information; outgoing letterpress correspondence (1894-1909, 1911-1912) regarding the above; also manuscripts and correspondence pertaining to the joint Cactaceae project with Nathaniel Lord Britton; manuscripts and correspondence about the joint project with John Donnell Smith regarding Hauyeae; reviews; and occasional newspaper clippings pertaining to botanists whose letters are located in the correspondence folders.
Index Terms
This collection is indexed under the following access terms. These are links to collections with related topics, persons or places.
Name
Britton, Nathaniel Lord, 1859-1934; Smith, John Donnell.; Rose, J. N. (Joseph Nelson), 1862-1928; United States Department of Agriculture. Division of Plants (USNM); United States National Herbarium. Division of Plants (USNM); United States National Herbarium. Department of Botany; Division of Botany (USDA); Division of Plants (USNM). United States Department of Agriculture; Division of Plants (USNM). United States National Herbarium
Subject
Botany
Physical Characteristics of Materials in the Collection
Scientific illustrations
- Incoming and Occasional Outgoing Correspondence (after 1910), 1886-1928. Arranged alphabetically and in most instances chronologically thereunder., Series 1
  Incoming correspondence, 1886-1928. For description of general contents see descriptive entry at the beginning of the finding aid.
  - Box 1
    - A (Box 1 of 44)
    - Abrams, LeRoy P. (1902-1927) (Box 1 of 44)
    - Alcocer, G. V. (in Spanish) (Box 1 of 44)
    - Alfaro, Anastasio (Box 1 of 44)
    - Allaire, C. B. (Box 1 of 44)
    - Allen, John A. (1892-1893). Includes address to the president and overseers of Harvard University, by Allen, concerning their neglect of the Botanic Garden at Harvard (1893). (Box 1 of 44)
    - Allen, O. D. (Box 1 of 44)
    - Altamirano, Fernando (1905-1907) (in Spanish) (Box 1 of 44)
    - Ames, Oakes (1903-1910) (Box 1 of 44)
    - Anderson, J. R. (Box 1 of 44)
    - Anderson, R. W. (Box 1 of 44)
    - Ba-Bk (Box 1 of 44)
    - Bl-Bu (Box 1 of 44)
    - Bailey, Liberty Hyde (1894-1927). Includes correspondence with Bailey and Wilhelm Miller regarding the Cyclopedia of American Horticulture (1898-1899). (Box 1 of 44)
    - Bailey, Vernon Orlando (Box 1 of 44)
    - Baker, Carl F. (1890-1908) (Box 1 of 44)
    - Baker, Edmund G. (1890-1903) (Box 1 of 44)
    - Ball, Carleton R. (1900-1910) (Box 1 of 44)
    - Barnhart, John Hendley (Box 1 of 44)
    - Barnes, Charles Reid (Box 1 of 44)
  - Box 2
    - Bartram, Edwin B. (Box 2 of 44)
    - Beadle, Chauncey D. (1896-1911) (Box 2 of 44)
    - Beal, W. J. (Box 2 of 44)
    - Bearss, J. T. (1908-1911) (Box 2 of 44)
    - Beattie, Rolla Kent (Box 2 of 44)
    - Beauverd, George (Box 2 of 44)
    - Bebb, Michael Schuck (1891-1895) (Box 2 of 44)
    - Berger, Alwin (1904-1927) (Box 2 of 44)
    - Berner, Glenn (Box 2 of 44)
    - Berry, W. A. (Box 2 of 44)
    - Bessey, Charles Edwin (1898-1910) (Box 2 of 44)
    - Bessey, Ernst A. (Box 2 of 44)
    - Bethel, E. (Box 2 of 44)
    - Bickwell, Eugene P. (Box 2 of 44)
    - Bisset, Peter (Box 2 of 44)
    - Blankinship, J. W. (1896-1908) (Box 2 of 44)
    - Blumer, J. C. (Box 2 of 44)
    - Bodeker, Father (Box 2 of 44)
    - Bogert, M. T. (Box 2 of 44)
    - Bonati, G. (Box 2 of 44)
    - Botanical Curiosities (Box 2 of 44)
    - Boyd, H. R. (Box 2 of 44)
    - Brainerd, Ezra (Box 2 of 44)
    - Brandegee, Katharine (1891-1909) (Box 2 of 44)
    - Brandegee, T. S. (1892-1911) (Box 2 of 44)
    - Brannon, Meluin A. (Box 2 of 44)
    - Braunton, Ernest B. (1902-1908) (Box 2 of 44)
    - Bray, William L. (1898-1908) (Box 2 of 44)
    - Briquet, John I. (Box 2 of 44)
    - Britton, Elizabeth Gertrude (1895-1911) (Box 2 of 44)
  - Box 3
    - Britton, Nathaniel Lord (1890-1922). Includes correspondence regarding botanical nomenclature. (8 folders) (Box 3 of 44)
  - Box 4
    - Britton, Nathaniel Lord (1913-1918) (6 folders) (Box 4 of 44)
  - Box 5
    - Britton, Nathaniel Lord (1919-1922) (6 folders) (Box 5 of 44)
  - Box 6
    - Britton, Nathaniel Lord (1923-1928) (4 folders) (Box 6 of 44)
    - Broadway, W. E. (Box 6 of 44)
    - Brockway, William (Box 6 of 44)
    - Brown, H. E. (Box 6 of 44)
    - Brown, Stewardson (Box 6 of 44)
    - Buiford, Joanna Mary (Box 6 of 44)
    - Burbank, Luther (Box 6 of 44)
    - Burnham, Stewart H. (Box 6 of 44)
    - Buscalioni, Luigi (Box 6 of 44)
    - Bush, B. F. (Box 6 of 44)
    - C (Box 6 of 44)
    - Canby, William M. (1890-1903) (Box 6 of 44)
  - Box 7
    - Candolle, Casimir de (Box 7 of 44)
    - Cannon, W. A. (Box 7 of 44)
    - Case, A. B. (Box 7 of 44)
    - Chaffey, Elswood (1910-1911) (Box 7 of 44)
    - Chamberlain, Edward B. (Box 7 of 44)
    - Chandler, Harley P. (Box 7 of 44)
    - Chapman, A. W. (Box 7 of 44)
    - Chesnut, V. K. (Box 7 of 44)
    - Chisolm, Frederic F. (Box 7 of 44)
    - Clark, H. Walton (Box 7 of 44)
    - Clemens, Joseph C. (Box 7 of 44)
    - Clements, Frederic E. (Box 7 of 44)
    - Cleveland, Daniel (Box 7 of 44)
    - Clute, Willard N. (Box 7 of 44)
    - Cockerell, Theodore D. A. (1896-1909) (Box 7 of 44)
    - Cogniaux, A. (1890-1896) (in French) (Box 7 of 44)
    - Collins, Frank S. (Box 7 of 44)
    - Collins, J. Franklin (Box 7 of 44)
    - Collom, Rose E. (Mrs.) (Box 7 of 44)
    - Commons, Albert (Box 7 of 44)
    - Conard, Henry Shoemaker (1904-1908) (Box 7 of 44)
    - Conzatti, Cassiano (1900-1927) (in Spanish) (Box 7 of 44)
    - Cook, Mel T. (Box 7 of 44)
    - Cook, Orator Fuller (Box 7 of 44)
    - Cooley, Grace E. (Box 7 of 44)
    - Coulter, John Merle (1891-1927) (Box 7 of 44)
    - Coulter and Rose. Contains letters and reviews concerning A Monograph of North American Umbelliferae. (Box 7 of 44)
    - Coulter, Stanley (Box 7 of 44)
  - Box 8
    - Coville, Frederick Vernon (1893-1927). Includes rough draft regarding the USNH collections; Rose letter regarding absence from administrative duties with the USNH (1912); outlining problems and accomplishments at the time (1912); in regard to having a new building to house the USNH in order to expand the collections (1927). (Box 8 of 44)
    - Crandall, Charles S. (Box 8 of 44)
    - Crawford, Joseph (Box 8 of 44)
    - Crider, Franklin J. (Box 8 of 44)
    - Cummings, Clara Eaton (1893-1905) (Box 8 of 44)
    - Curtiss, A. H. (Box 8 of 44)
    - Cusick, William C. (Box 8 of 44)
    - D. Includes postcard from Domin to Rose (1911?) with photograph of Domin that was placed in the photo archives of the Hunt Institute. (Box 8 of 44)
    - Davenport, George E. (1892-1900) (Box 8 of 44)
    - Davidson, A. (Box 8 of 44)
    - Davies, D. C. (Box 8 of 44)
    - Davison, Wilfred P. (Box 8 of 44)
    - Davy, Joseph Burtt (Box 8 of 44)
    - Day, Mary Alice (Box 8 of 44)
    - Deam, Charles Clemon (1902-1925) (Box 8 of 44)
    - Deane, Walter (1891-1927) (2 folders) (Box 8 of 44)
    - DeLaet, Frantz (Box 8 of 44)
    - Dewey, Lyster Hoxie (1893-1911) (Box 8 of 44)
    - Dodd, Alan P. (Box 8 of 44)
    - Dodge, Charles K. (Box 8 of 44)
    - Dorsett, P. H. (Box 8 of 44)
    - Dousa, B. C. (Box 8 of 44)
  - Box 9
    - Dowell, Philip (1902-1911) (Box 9 of 44)
    - Drude, Oscar (Box 9 of 44)
    - Duges, Alfred (Box 9 of 44)
    - Dyer, W. T. Thiselton (should be Thiselton-Dyer, William Turner) (Box 9 of 44)
    - Dyott, G. M. (Box 9 of 44)
    - E (Box 9 of 44)
    - Earle, F. S. (Box 9 of 44)
    - Eastwood, Alice (1892-1927) (Box 9 of 44)
    - Eaton, A. A. (Box 9 of 44)
    - Edison, Thomas Alva. Rubber Exploration (1927) (Box 9 of 44)
    - Edson, William L. G. (Box 9 of 44)
    - Eggleston, W. W. (Box 9 of 44)
    - Eichlam, Federico (1908-1912) (In German) (Box 9 of 44)
    - Ekman, Erik L. (Box 9 of 44)
    - Elizalde, Rafael H. (Box 9 of 44)
    - Elmer, A. D. E. (Box 9 of 44)
    - Engler, Adolphe (Box 9 of 44)
    - Ericksson, Jakob (Box 9 of 44)
    - Evermann, Barton Warren (1893-1923) (Box 9 of 44)
    - F (Box 9 of 44)
    - Fairchild, David G. (1903-1911) (Box 9 of 44)
    - Farlow, W. G. (Box 9 of 44)
    - Farwell, O. Atkins (Box 9 of 44)
    - Fawcett, William (Box 9 of 44)
    - Faxon, Charles Edward (1891-1897) (Box 9 of 44)
  - Box 10
    - Fedde, Friedrich (Box 10 of 44)
    - Ferguson, A. M. (Box 10 of 44)
    - Fernald, Merritt Lyndon (1893-1911) (Box 10 of 44)
    - Ferriss, James H. (Box 10 of 44)
    - Field, Marshall Jr. (Box 10 of 44)
    - Fink, Bruce (1907-1912) (Box 10 of 44)
    - Fisher, Elmon M. (Box 10 of 44)
    - Flores, Leopoldo (1904). Includes drawings by Thomas T. Reed. (Box 10 of 44)
    - Foex, Felix (Box 10 of 44)
    - Foraker, C. T. (Box 10 of 44)
    - Franceschi, Emanuel Francesco (1895-1903) (Box 10 of 44)
    - Francis, W. H. (Box 10 of 44)
    - Franck, Harry (Box 10 of 44)
    - Freeman, George F. (Box 10 of 44)
    - Fric, A. V. (1923-1927) (in German with translations) (Box 10 of 44)
    - Friedlander, R. (Box 10 of 44)
    - Frye, Theodore Christian (1903-1910) (Box 10 of 44)
    - G (Box 10 of 44)
    - Gaillard, D. D. (Box 10 of 44)
    - Gaillard, Katherine D. (Box 10 of 44)
    - Gallaher, Philip M. (Box 10 of 44)
    - Galloway, B. T. (Box 10 of 44)
    - Gandoger, Michel (Box 10 of 44)
    - Garman, H. (Box 10 of 44)
    - Garrett, A. O. (Box 10 of 44)
    - Gaumer, George F. (Box 10 of 44)
    - Glatfelder, N. M. (Box 10 of 44)
    - Goldman, Edward Alphonso (1897-1911). Expedition reports from Mexico and California. (Box 10 of 44)
    - Goodwin, Irving A. (Box 10 of 44)
    - Gray, Asa (Box 10 of 44)
    - Greene, Edward L. (1889-1904) (Box 10 of 44)
  - Box 11
    - Greenman, Jesse More (1895-1911) (Box 11 of 44)
    - Griffiths, David (Box 11 of 44)
    - Griggs, Robert F. (Box 11 of 44)
    - Grout, A. J. (Box 11 of 44)
    - Guayule Bush (Box 11 of 44)
    - Guzman, David J. (Box 11 of 44)
    - H (Box 11 of 44)
    - Haines, Alfred S. (Box 11 of 44)
    - Hall, Fred H. (Box 11 of 44)
    - Hall, Harvey Monroe (1902-1912) (Box 11 of 44)
    - Hamet, Raymond (Box 11 of 44)
    - Hammond, Charles (Box 11 of 44)
    - Harms, H. (Box 11 of 44)
    - Harned, Joseph E. (Box 11 of 44)
    - Harper, Roland M. (1900-1911) (Box 11 of 44)
    - Harris, Edward (Box 11 of 44)
    - Harshberger, John William (1903, 1910) (Box 11 of 44)
    - Hasse, Hermann Edward (1891-1912) (Box 11 of 44)
    - Heimerl, Anton (in German) (Box 11 of 44)
    - Heller, A. A. (1892-1911) (Box 11 of 44)
  - Box 12
    - Hemsley, W. Botting (1890-1910) (Box 12 of 44)
    - Henderson, Louis Forniquet (c. 1893-1900). Contains SI Registrar stamped correspondence. (Box 12 of 44)
    - Henderson, Peter (1892-1898) (Box 12 of 44)
    - Henry, Augustine (Box 12 of 44)
    - Herre, Albert C. (1907-1912) (Box 12 of 44)
    - Herrera, Alfonso L. (Box 12 of 44)
    - Herrera, Fortunato L. (Box 12 of 44)
    - Hertrich, William (1927) (Box 12 of 44)
    - Hill, Arthur W. (Box 12 of 44)
    - Hill, E. J. (Box 12 of 44)
    - Hitchcock, Albert Spear (1901-1912) (Box 12 of 44)
    - Hochderffer, George (Box 12 of 44)
    - Hoffmann, O. (Box 12 of 44)
    - Holm, Theodore (Box 12 of 44)
    - Holway, E. W. D. (Box 12 of 44)
    - Holzinger, John M. (1893-1911) (Box 12 of 44)
    - Hope, C. W. (Box 12 of 44)
    - Hough, Romeyn Beck (Box 12 of 44)
    - Hough, Walter L. (Box 12 of 44)
    - House, Homer D. (Box 12 of 44)
    - Howard, L. O. (Box 12 of 44)
    - Howe, Marshall Avery (1899-1909) (Box 12 of 44)
    - Howe, Reginald Heber Jr. (1909-1911) (Box 12 of 44)
    - Howell, Thomas Jefferson (1896-1902) (Box 12 of 44)
    - Hunter, J. S. (Box 12 of 44)
    - Ingraham, Rhoby A. (Box 12 of 44)
    - Irish, H. C. (Box 12 of 44)
    - J (Box 12 of 44)
    - Jackson, B. Daydon (Box 12 of 44)
    - Jaeger, Edmund C. (Box 12 of 44)
    - Jansen, Thomas (Box 12 of 44)
    - Jepson, Willis Linn (1897-1911) (Box 12 of 44)
    - Jermy, Julius (Box 12 of 44)
    - Johnson, Duncan S. (Box 12 of 44)
  - Box 13
    - Johnston, Ivan Murray (1922-1926) (Box 13 of 44)
    - Jones, Marcus E. (1893-1923) (Box 13 of 44)
    - K (Box 13 of 44)
    - Kearney, Thomas Henry Jr. (1899-1900) (Box 13 of 44)
    - Kellerman, William Ashbrook (1905-1908) (Box 13 of 44)
    - Kelsey, Harlan P. (1892-1894) (Box 13 of 44)
    - Kelsey, F. D. (Box 13 of 44)
    - Knapp, Abbie R. (Box 13 of 44)
    - Koehne, E. (Box 13 of 44)
    - Krieger, Louis C. C. (Box 13 of 44)
    - Kuester, Arthur (Box 13 of 44)
    - Kunze, Richard Ernest (1902-1911) (Box 13 of 44)
    - L (Box 13 of 44)
    - Lamb, Frank H. (Box 13 of 44)
    - Lamson-Scribner, F. (Box 13 of 44)
    - Leavitt, Robert G. (Box 13 of 44)
    - Leiberg, John B. (1894-1910) (Box 13 of 44)
    - Lemmon, John Gill (1889-1904) (Box 13 of 44)
    - Letts, Arthur (Box 13 of 44)
    - Lloyd, Francis Ernest (1907-1910) (Box 13 of 44)
    - Lloyd Library and Lloyd Brothers (Box 13 of 44)
    - Locke, Otto (Box 13 of 44)
    - Loesener, Thomas (Box 13 of 44)
    - Lumholtz, Carl (Box 13 of 44)
    - Lunell, J. (Box 13 of 44)
  - Box 14
    - M (includes Clinton Hart Merriam correspondence) (Box 14 of 44)
    - Macbride, J. Francis (Box 14 of 44)
    - MacDougal, Daniel Trembly (1892-1927) (3 folders) (Box 14 of 44)
    - MacElwee, Alexander (Box 14 of 44)
    - Macfarlane, John M. (1904-1908) (Box 14 of 44)
    - Mackensen, Bernard (1909-1911) (Box 14 of 44)
    - Mackenzie, Kenneth K. (Box 14 of 44)
    - Macoun, James M. (1887-1906) (Box 14 of 44)
    - Maiden, Joseph Henry (1900). Frederick Vernon Coville to Maiden stating that all specimens received by the USDA are eventually transferred to the USNH, even those originally kept out for economic investigations (July 12, 1900). (Box 14 of 44)
    - Mason, S. C. (Box 14 of 44)
    - Masters, Maxwell T. (Box 14 of 44)
    - Maximowicz, C. J. (Box 14 of 44)
    - Maxon, William Ralph (1899-1911). Copy of appointment in cryptoganic botany (1899); mostly regarding Maxon's collecting expeditions written from the field; also Rose correspondence when the latter was out collecting in Arizona and Mexico (1910). (2 folders) (Box 14 of 44)
  - Box 15
    - McAtee, Waldo Lee (Box 15 of 44)
    - MaCalla, W. C. (Box 15 of 44)
    - McGregor, Ernest A. (Box 15 of 44)
    - Mearns, Edgar Alexander (1896-1909) (Box 15 of 44)
    - Medsger, O. P. (Box 15 of 44)
    - Meehan, Thomas and Sons (Box 15 of 44)
    - Mell, C. D. (Box 15 of 44)
    - Merriam, Clinton Hart (Box 15 of 44)
    - Merriam, John Campbell (Box 15 of 44)
    - Merrill, Elmer Drew (1900-1927) (Box 15 of 44)
    - Metcalfe, O. B. (Box 15 of 44)
    - Meyer, W. F. (Box 15 of 44)
    - Michelli, M. (Box 15 of 44)
    - Miller, Gerrit Smith Jr. (1901-1904) (Box 15 of 44)
    - Miller, H. M. A. (Box 15 of 44)
    - Miller, O. O. (Box 15 of 44)
    - Miller, Wilhelm (see also Liberty Hyde Bailey) (Box 15 of 44)
    - Mills, William Webster (Box 15 of 44)
    - Millspaugh, Charles Frederick (1891-1923) (Box 15 of 44)
    - Moeller, Arturo F. (Box 15 of 44)
    - Mohr, Charles Theodore (1892-1901) (Box 15 of 44)
    - Mooney, James (1898-1904) (Box 15 of 44)
    - Moore, Albert Hanford (Box 15 of 44)
    - Moore, George T. (Box 15 of 44)
    - Morris, D. (Box 15 of 44)
    - Morris, E. L. (Box 15 of 44)
    - Moseley, E. L. (Box 15 of 44)
    - Muller, Willy (Box 15 of 44)
    - Mundt, Walter (Box 15 of 44)
    - Munson, T. V. (Box 15 of 44)
    - Murrill, William Alphonso (1923) (Box 15 of 44)
    - N (Box 15 of 44)
    - Nakai, T (Box 15 of 44)
    - Nash, George V. (Box 15 of 44)
    - Nelson, Aven (1896-1926) (Box 15 of 44)
    - Nelson, Edward W. (1894-1909) (Box 15 of 44)
    - Nieuwland, J. A. (Box 15 of 44)
    - Nichols, George E. (Box 15 of 44)
    - Norton, J. B. S. (Box 15 of 44)
  - Box 16
    - O (Box 16 of 44)
    - Oliver, G. W. (Box 16 of 44)
    - Olsson-Seffer, Pehr (Box 16 of 44)
    - Orcutt, Charles Russell (1898-1927) (2 folders) (Box 16 of 44)
    - Ortega, Jesus Gonzalez (Box 16 of 44)
    - Osterhout, George E. (Box 16 of 44)
    - P (Box 16 of 44)
    - Pachano, Abelardo (Box 16 of 44)
    - Painter, Joseph Hannum (Box 16 of 44)
    - Palmer, William (Box 16 of 44)
    - Pammel, L. H. (Box 16 of 44)
    - Pampanini, Renato (Box 16 of 44)
    - Parish, Samuel B. (1893-1923) (Box 16 of 44)
    - Patten, Juliet C. (Box 16 of 44)
    - Paul, Oglesby (Box 16 of 44)
    - Pearson, G. A. (Box 16 of 44)
    - Pearson, William H. (Box 16 of 44)
    - Pennell, Francis Whittier (1909-1924) (Box 16 of 44)
    - Perkins, I. (Box 16 of 44)
    - Perredes, P. E. F. (Box 16 of 44)
    - Pieters, A. J. (Box 16 of 44)
    - Pilger, R. (Box 16 of 44)
    - Piper, Charles Vancouver (1897-1924) (Box 16 of 44)
    - Pittier, Henri (1897-1925) (Box 16 of 44)
    - Plank, E. N. (Box 16 of 44)
    - Pollard, Charles Louis (1896-1908) (Box 16 of 44)
  - Box 17
    - Pond, Mrs. Thomas G. (Box 17 of 44)
    - Prain, D. (Box 17 of 44)
    - Pringle, Clyde Guernsey (1891-1911) (2 folders) (Box 17 of 44)
    - Purpus, Carl A. (1899-1927) (3 folders) (Box 17 of 44)
    - Purpus, J. A. (Box 17 of 44)
    - Q (Box 17 of 44)
    - Quehl, Leopold (1907-1911) (in German with translations) (Box 17 of 44)
    - R (Box 17 of 44)
    - Radlkofer, L. (Box 17 of 44)
    - Ramirez, Jose (Box 17 of 44)
    - Rathbun, Richard (1908-1911). Includes letter to Rose regarding the use of USNM facilities, having franking privileges for official correspondence that is to be kept part of USNM files, and an aid, while working with Carnegie Institution of Washington (December 11, 1911). (Box 17 of 44)
    - Ravenel, William deC. (1924-1927) (Box 17 of 44)
    - Record, Samuel J. (Box 17 of 44)
    - Rehder, Alfred (1902-1904) (Box 17 of 44)
    - Reko, Blas P. (Box 17 of 44)
    - Reverchon, J. (1896-1907) (Box 17 of 44)
  - Box 18
    - Reynolds, Ernest Shaw (Box 18 of 44)
    - Rhoads, S. A. (Box 18 of 44)
    - Ricker, Perry LeRoy (1902-1909) (Box 18 of 44)
    - Robinson, Benjamin Lincoln (1890-1924) (3 folders) (Box 18 of 44)
    - Robinson, Charles Budd (1902-1907) (Box 18 of 44)
    - Robinson, J. H. (Box 18 of 44)
    - Roland-Gosselin, R. (Box 18 of 44)
    - Rolfs, P. H. (Box 18 of 44)